Guide to the Jonathan Edwards Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jonathan Edwards collection
1696-1972
1726-1758
GEN MSS 151
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18
(39 boxes)
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, documents, printed materials, photographs, and artifacts documenting the lives and work of Jonathan Edwards and his family. Jonathan Edwards' papers contain the great majority of his surviving manuscripts. These include over one thousand sermons; private theological and philosophical notebooks, including the nine volume "Miscellanies" and four volume "Notes on the Scripture;" Edwards'interleaved Bible. In addition, there is a box of Jonathan Edwards' correspondence; principal correspondents include Joseph Bellamy and Thomas Foxcroft. Other Edwards family papers include several of Timothy Edwards's sermon notebooks; correspondence belonging to Jonathan Edwards (1745-1801), Jonathan Walter Edwards, and Hannah Edwards Wetmore (principal correspondents are Calvin Chapin, Moses Tryon, Joseph Bellamy, Lucy Wetmore Whittelsey and Chauncey Whittelsey); printed material (chiefly numerous family Bibles) and a broadside Thanksgiving Proclamation by George Washington dated October 1789; photographs of Edwards family members; and papers relating to the history of the collection.
Other Storage Formats: oversize, microfilm
Edwards, Jonathan, 1703-1758
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the Jonathan Edwards Collection came to Yale as a gift of the heirs of Jonathan Edwards in 1900. Additional individual pieces, small groups of his papers, and especially, other family papers, have been added over the years through gift and purchase, chiefly from other Edwards descendants. For further acquisitions information, please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Though the bulk of Edwards's manuscripts are at Yale, other institutions do possess important pieces. The Franklin Trask Library of Andover Newton Theological School (Newton Center, Mass.) has a small yet significant collection of Edwards manuscripts, including a large number of family letters, several of Edwards's early "scientific" essays, and Book 6 of the "Miscellanies," containing entries 1067 and 1068, relating to the prophecies of the Messiah. The manuscript of the "Spider Letter" is at the New-York Historical Society. Certain manuscripts, however, are not known to have survived. Among Edwards's autobiographical writings, for example, neither the "Diary" nor the "Personal Narrative" are thought to be extant. Though an index for the notes on "The Mind" has survived, the main text itself has not. For these writings, readers should consult printed editions of Edwards' works.
JONATHAN EDWARDS (1703-1758)
Jonathan Edwards, among the foremost theologians and philosophers of his time, was born in East Windsor, Connecticut, on October 5, 1703. He attended Yale College and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in 1720. He returned in 1723 to receive his Master of Arts degree, and served as a tutor from 1724 to 1726. Upon leaving Yale, he succeeded his grandfather, Solomon Stoddard, as minister of the Congregationalist Church at Northampton, Massachusetts from 1726 to 1750. There he became known as an evangelical preacher and stern Calvinist, helping inspire the "Great Awakening" of the 1740s. His writings, which were widely circulated, included A Faithful Narrative, Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God, Distinguishing Marks of a Work of the Spirit of God, Some Thoughts Concerning the Revivals, and A Treatise Concerning Religious Affections.
Edwards eventually became alienated from his Northampton congregation, and was dismissed after a protracted controversy over qualifications for church membership. In 1751 he became a missionary to the Mahican and Mohawk Indians at Stockbridge, Massachusetts, and minister to the English congregation there. While at Stockbridge he continued writing treatises that expounded his theology, including Freedom of the Will, Original Sin, The Nature of True Virtue, and The End for Which God Created the World. In 1757, he accepted an offer to become the president of the College of New Jersey, now Princeton University. In March 1758 he received a smallpox innoculation which proved to be infected, and died.
For more information on Edwards's life, see Perry Miller, Jonathan Edwards (New York: Sloan, 1949); Ola E. Winslow, Jonathan Edwards, 1703-1758: A Biography (New York: Macmillan, 1941); and Iain H. Murray, Jonathan Edwards: A New Biography (Carlisle, Penn.: Banner of Truth, 1987). Readers should also consult The Works of Jonathan Edwards (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1957-ongoing) for further definitive information on Edwards's life and writings.
JONATHAN EDWARDS FAMILY
Note: The people listed here are represented prominently in the collection, and are therefore mentioned in the Description of the Collection.
Timothy Edwards (1669-1758) m. (1694) Esther Stoddard (1672-1771)
Jonathan Edwards (1703-1758) m. (1727) Sarah Pierpont (1710-1758)
Jonathan (1745-1801) m. (1770) Mary Porter
Mary m. James Hait [Hoyt?]
Jonathan Walter m. Elizabeth Tryon (daughter of Moses Tryon)
Jonathan
9 other children
Jerusha m. Calvin Chapin
Ten children
Hannah (1713-1773) m. (1746) Seth Wetmore (1700-1778)
Lucy (1749-1826) m. (1770) Chauncey Whittelsey (d. 1812)
Nine daughters
Scope and Contents
The Jonathan Edwards Collection consists of writings, correspondence, documents, printed materials, photographs, and artifacts documenting the lives and work of Jonathan Edwards and his family. The collection spans the years 1696-1972, but the bulk of the material dates from 1726-1758, during the years of Jonathan Edwards's ministry. The collection contains the great majority of Edwards's surviving manuscripts, and as such is a particularly rich resource for examining the man and his theology.
The Collection is housed in 38 boxes and is organized in ten series: Writings of Jonathan Edwards, Jonathan Edwards Correspondence, Church Papers, Edwards Family Writings, Edwards Family Correspondence, Genealogical Notes and Other Family Papers, Printed Material, Visual Material, Artifacts, and History of the Collection. Box 38 contains Oversize items.
Series I, Writings of Jonathan Edwards (ca. 1720-1784), the largest series in the collection, is organized into three subseries: Sermons, Notebooks and Memoranda, and Personal Writings. There are over one thousand sermons, enabling the reader to track Edwards's homiletic activities over his entire career. The sermons are arranged in the order of the books of the Bible. A page number in parentheses refers to the page on which the doctrine or subject is found.
Edwards often wrote on odd pieces of paper that had been sewn together, and there is ample evidence of this habit in the Writings. These scraps may be anything from blank space on a letter he received, blank areas of printed items such as broadsides and newspapers, prayer requests from his congregation, and scraps from his daughters' painted paper fans (as described in Jane Greenfield's "Notable Bindings VIII," Yale University Gazette 68 [October 1993] 70-73). The sermons are an average 4" x 4", and the oversize sermons, housed in boxes 13 and 14 and also arranged in canonical order, are approximately 6" x 4". The sewing of these booklets indicates the order of construction, often giving clues to later revisions and additions.
Generally speaking, sermons written before 1742 are fully written out, but after that date they appear in outline form and are increasingly difficult to read. Edwards began to date his sermons in 1733, and it may be assumed that undated sermons which have the scripture text or the first page present were likely written before that date. It should be noted that until 1752 the Julian calendar was used, and dates on the sermons and correspondence in this collection reflect dating practices common at that time. Edwards had a practice of "reusing" his sermons, in some cases tipping in new parts of a sermon, in others simply bracketing parts of the sermon he wished to use. Those he altered carry multiple dates. Notes by The Works of Jonathan Edwards staff, used to identify and date many of the sermons, have been photocopied onto acid-free paper and are included with them.
Three sermon notebooks accompany the sermons, one of them containing a note for the Farewell Sermon Edwards gave at Northampton (box 14, folder 1154). There are also thirty-four folders of fragments, some with notes from others on the verso.
The sermons are supplemented by Edwards's private theological and philosophical notebooks and memoranda. These notebooks range from nearly finished versions of treatises to rough jottings. They are in a larger format than the sermons (mostly folio), and some are written in the margins of printed newspapers, broadsides, and books. A number of notebooks are dedicated to single themes, some of which are notes toward published materials. Included among the 41 notebooks are the nine volumes of "Miscellanies," eight volumes of theological notes composed of 1,360 entries of varying length, with an index created by Edwards; and four volumes of "Notes on the Scripture." There is also an interleaved Bible Edwards acquired from his brother-in-law, which is a disbound copy of the King James version of the Bible, interleaved with blank folio paper (box 17, folder 1216). There are detailed notes on every interleaved page relating to the text of the Bible opposite the page.
The Personal Writings section contains only five items, including a diary and memorandum book kept from 1733-1757 (box 21, folder 1267), and a copy of Edwards's will, dated March 1753, written in an unidentified hand (box 21, folder 1270). The original is in the Hampshire County Court House, Northampton, Massachusetts.
Series II, Jonathan Edwards Correspondence (ca. 1735-1757), highlights Edwards's activities as a parent, pastor, and entrepreneur, his contacts with English and Scottish divines, and his efforts to publish such works as the Humble Inquiry and Freedom of the Will. The series is housed in one box and is organized into Outgoing Letters, Incoming Letters, and Third Party Correspondence. Principal correspondents include Joseph Bellamy and Thomas Foxcroft. Third Party Correspondence contains three letters written by others but concerning Jonathan Edwards. Series III, Church Papers (1735-1751), is arranged chronologically and is housed in one box. It consists mostly of reports of meetings of the First Parish at Northampton. Included is the report of the council which voted the dismissal of Edwards in June 1750 (box 23, folder 1350).
The rest of the collection relates primarily to Jonathan Edwards's family and descendants, and to the history of the Jonathan Edwards papers prior to their arrival at Yale in 1900. Among these family members most frequently represented are Jonathan Edwards's father, Timothy Edwards (1669-1758), minister of East Windsor, Connecticut; son Jonathan Edwards (1745-1801) and his son Jonathan Walter Edwards; and sister Hannah Edwards Wetmore (1713-1773) and her daughter Lucy Wetmore Whittelsey.
Series IV, Edwards Family Writings (1704-1904), is arranged alphabetically by author and then by title. There are a large number of religious writings such as sermons and confessions of faith, as well as personal diaries. Included are Timothy Edwards's sermon notebooks, the journal of Jonathan Edwards (1841-1886), kept while he was a child, four sermons by Chauncey Whittelsey, and a "memoranda" written by a Mrs. Pearce after the death of her husband, on a piece of paper joined to itself, which may have been worn as an armband (box 24, folder 1376). There are also fourteen sermons and other writings by unidentified authors.
Series V, Edwards Family Correspondence (1715-1908) is organized into four subseries: Jonathan Edwards (1745-1801), Jonathan Walter Edwards, Hannah Edwards Wetmore, and Other Correspondents. In Jonathan Edwards's correspondence, there are seven folders of letters to his son Jonathan Walter Edwards, and two folders of letters from Calvin Chapin. Principal correspondents of Jonathan Walters Edwards include a Jonathan Edwards (whose letters date from 1814-1819), Moses Tryon, and Mary Edwards Hoyt. Hannah Edwards Wetmore's letters include letters from John Sargeant, a suitor of hers whose presence caused a rift with her betrothed, a Mr. Rockwell. A paper in Series X entitled, "Hard Hearted Hannah" by John De K. Alsop discusses this correspondence (box 37, folder 1669). The Other Correspondents file includes letters to Joseph Bellamy, Samuel Andrew Law, Chauncey Whittelsey, and Lucy Wetmore Whittelsey.
Series VI, Genealogical Notes and Other Family Papers (1696-1891), is housed a single box. Besides the genealogical notes, it includes documents such as wills, indentures, deeds, certificates, a prayer in Mahican (box 29, folder 1596), and a bound volume of manuscript poems and printed illustrations belonging to Lydia Eliza Hollingsworth Kennedy (box 29, folder 1605).
Series VII, Printed Material, is arranged alphabetically by title when known, or type of material; family Bibles and other volumes, however, are listed at the end of the series, as stored. The series includes pamphlets, ephemera removed from (and referenced to) family Bibles, clippings, an array of Bibles and religious works belonging to family members, and a broadside Thanksgiving Proclamation by George Washington in October 1789 (box 38, folder 1682).
Series VIII, Visual Material (1783-1908), contains a box of vintage cabinet cards, daguerreotypes, engravings, silhouettes, and photographic postcards of Edwards family members.
Series IX, Artifacts, includes a scrap of Sarah Pierpont Edwards's wedding dress and a linen bedsheet made by Esther Stoddard Edwards (box 36, folder 1656).
Series X, History of the Papers (1767-1972) is organized into two sections: Correspondence, arranged by correspondent, and Agreements, Inventories, and Related Papers, arranged alphabetically by type. The correspondence consists of letters between descendants of Edwards, and regards the disposition of the papers.
Appendix A: Guide to the Microfilm
Series I, Writings of Jonathan Edwards, is housed in boxes 1-21 and is organized into three subseries: Sermons (boxes 1-15), Notebooks and Memoranda (boxes 15-21), and Personal Writings (box 21).
MS Vault film 1086 1 1 1-48 First oversize target should be before folder 1, not after.
MS Vault film 1087 2 1-2 49-96
MS Vault film 1088 3 2 97-143
MS Vault film 1089 4 2-3 144-191
MS Vault film 1090 5 3 192-244
MS Vault film 1091 6 4 245-295
MS Vault film 1092 7 4-5 296-333
MS Vault film 1093 8 5 334-377
MS Vault film 1094 9 5-6 378-427
MS Vault film 1095 10 6 428-475
MS Vault film 1096 11 6-7 476-524
MS Vault film 1097 12 7-8 525-574
MS Vault film 1098 13 8 575-617
MS Vault film 1099 14 8-9 618-667
MS Vault film 1100 15 9 668-712
MS Vault film 1101 16 10 713-755
MS Vault film 1102 17 10-11 756-796
MS Vault film 1103 18 11 797-845
MS Vault film 1104 19 11-12 846-893
MS Vault film 1105 20 12 894-933
MS Vault film 1106 21 13 934-1054
MS Vault film 1107 22 13-14 1055-1154
MS Vault film 110 23 14-15 1155-1199
Calvinism -- United States; Congregationalism -- Sermons; Great Awakening; Indians of North America -- Missions -- Massachusetts; Preaching -- United States -- History -- 17th century; Revivals -- Massachusetts -- Northampton; Theology, Doctrinal -- United States -- History; Northampton (Mass.) -- History -- Sources; Artifacts (object genre); Broadsides (notices); Cabinet photographs; Card photographs (photographs); Church records; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Diaries; Family papers; Genealogies (histories); Photographic prints; Sermons; Clergy; Bellamy, Joseph, 1719-1790; Chapin, Calvin, 1763-1851; Edwards, Jonathan Walter; Edwards, Jonathan, 1703-1758; Edwards, Jonathan, 1745-1801; Edwards, Timothy, 1669-1758; Foxcroft, Thomas, 1697-1769; Tryon, Moses; Wetmore, Hannah Edwards, 1713-1773; Whittelsey, Chauncey, 1746-1812; Whittelsey, Lucy Wetmore, 1749-1826; Edwards family
- Writings of Jonathan Edwards, c. 1720-84; Series I; 10.3; (21 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings of Jonathan Edwards, is organized in three subseries: Sermons; Notebooks and Memoranda; and Personal Writings. Sermons have been arranged by Biblical text, with sermon notebooks and unidentified fragments placed at the end of the subseries. Box 13 contains larger format sermons. Notebooks and Memoranda and Personal Writings are arranged alphabetically by title, subject, or type of material.
  - SERMONS
    - GEN. 1:27: "That God has given men reason and understanding...man being made in God's image...made holy..." (p. 2), 1751 Aug
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Box 13, folder 934
      Preached to Stockbridge Indians and Mohawks
    - GEN. 3:4: "One principal means that the devil makes use of to persuade men to sin is to persuade 'em that they shall escape punishment", 1740 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - GEN. 3:11: "The act of our first father in eating the forbidden fruit was a very heinous act" (p.5), four sermons, 1738[/9] Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - GEN. 3:24: "When man fell, God drove him away from all his former blessedness" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - GEN. 3:17-19: Re: "the circumstances of the fall" (p. 1), fragment, [post 1756 Mar]
      See: Box 13, folder 935
    - GEN. 4:3-5: "It has been a thing established in the Church of Christ from the very beginning that His people should publicly offer up a part of their worldly subsistence to God as a part of the stated publick service of His visible church" (p. 8), 1743 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Thanksgiving
    - GEN. 4:7: "That wicked mens sins lie at their door" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - GEN. 6:22: "We should be willing to engage in and go through with that which is a great undertaking in order to our own salvation" (p. 2), [1740] Sep (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - GEN. 12:2: "Tis what is greatly to be desired to be blessed of God ourselves and to [be] made blessings unto others" (p. 4), 1737, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - GEN. 15:1: "...three parts...1. His shield of his people. 2. Exceeding great reward. 3. That therefore no cause to fear" (p. 1), 1742 Jul (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - GEN. 19:14: "The reason why men no more regard warnings of future punishment is because it don't seem real to them" (p. 3) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - GEN. 19:17: "Tis needful for those that seek an escape from God's wrath to avoid these things: lingering, looking back and trusting in anything short of the true refuge" (p. 1), [1741?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - GEN. 24:58: "I would in the first place shew...that Rebekah in this affair is a type of the church and the believing soul in its mystical marriage with Christ" (p. 1), 1742 Jul (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - GEN. 27:39: "Those that God hates he is notwithstanding often times willing to give em a plenty of these earthly things and the choicest of them" (p. 4), 1741 Apr (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - GEN. 28:12: "The ladder which God has set on the earth for men to ascend to happiness reaches even unto heaven" (p. 6), 1736 Mar (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - GEN. 32:24-32: "Jesus Christ remembers a people in the time of their troubles and difficulties and will come to em and take care of em" (p. 1), 1754 May
      See: Box 13, folder 936
      Preached to Stockbridge Indians
    - GEN. 32:24-26: "Tis frequently God's manner when persons are seeking the blessing of him to exercise them with trials of their resolution and steadfastness in seeking before he bestows it upon them" (p. 7), 1735 Aug (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - GEN. 32:26-29: "The way to obtain the blessing of God is not to let God go except he bless us" (p. 5), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - GEN. 39:12: "Tis our duty not only to avoid those things that are themselves sinful, but also, as far as may be, those things that lead and expose to sin" (p. 6), 1738, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - GEN. 43:3: "...Joseph was a remarkable type of Christ" (p. 1), 1741/2 Feb (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - EX. 8:15: "Observe particularly how the case was with Pharoah with regard to that misimprovement of respite from God's judgments which we read of in the text" (p. 1), 1749 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      "Public fast for rain"
    - EX. 8:18: "Satan's power is a limited power" (p. 2), 1734 Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - EX. 9:12-16: "They that will not yield to the power of God's word shall be broken by the power of his hand" (p. 2), 1747 Jul (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - EX. 9:16: "Some persons are raised up to be in a peculiar manner beyond other sinners the awful monuments of the glory of God's justice and great wrath" (p. 2), 1743 Aug (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - EX. 10:9: "Then do a people praise God in a becoming manner when all sorts among them are united in it and when they do it with all that they have" (p. 3), 1741 Nov (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Thanksgiving sermon
    - EX. 13:18: "When God truly delivers men from spiritual bondage, they go forth prepared both to travel and to fight as soldiers to war," (p. 1), 1743 Apr (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - EX. 16:20: "For persons to lay up past experiences to live upon them so as to content themselves with them without daily seeking new ones, is the way to have an occasion of those things in them that are very bothersome hurtful and troublesome" (p. 1), 1741 Oct (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - EX. 16:21: "The heavenly manna is rarely found by those that neglect to gather it till late in the day" (p. 1), 1741 Oct (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - EX. 19:4: "God carries his people along through the world towards glory far above the reach of all their enemies or anything that might hinder their blessedness" (p. 5) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - EX. 20:15: "An unjust usurping of our neighbor's property without his consent [forbidden by 8th commandment]" (pp. 2-3), 1740 Jul (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - EX. 20:24: "That if we would be in the way of God's grace and blessing we must wait upon him in his own way and in the use of his appointed means" (p. 3) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - EX. 33:18-19: "God's goodness is that wherein his glory doth eminently appear to the children of men" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - EX. 33:19: "Subject: the sovereignty of God's mercy" (p. 1), 1746, 1754 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      "Thanksgiving for victory over the rebels"
    - EX. 34:6-7: "God is an infinitely merciful and gracious God" (p. 1), 1753 Jan
      See: Box 13, folder 937
    - LEV. 26:3-13: "For a people to walk in a way of obedience to the commands of God is the way for them to be every way blessed of him" (p. 1), 1744/5 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      "Publick Fast"
    - NUM. 11:10-15: "I. ...Moses' complaint of the great burden and trouble of that office and work which God had appointed him to of leading the children of Israel through the wilderness to Canaan..." (p. 1), 1739/40 Feb (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - NUM. 12:6-8: "Moses was a person very highly favored and privileged of God" (p. 1), 1745 Jun (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - NUM. 12:9: "God's departure from those who have been favoured with the special tokens of his presence is an awful token of his anger" (p. 1), 1748 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Fast sermon
    - NUM. 13:27-28: "There are some professors of religion that like very well some things in the blessings God has promised to his people that yet wholly dislike 'em as they are offered and bring up an evil report of em" (p. 4), 1745 Jun (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - NUM. 14:21: "The glory and honor of God requires that his displeasure be manifested against sin" (p. 3) (Box 1, Folder 36)